Emily Tseng

New York, NY | et397@cornell.edu | emtseng.me

RESEARCH INTERESTS

I am interested in human-computer interaction (HCI), information and communication technologies for development (ICTD) and ubiquitous computing in the context of health technology. In particular, I aim to investigate how novel applications of sensing and natural language processing (NLP) in physical, behavioral and mental health might improve wellbeing for underserved people.

EDUCATION

- 2019 present *Ph.D. student, Information Science,* **Cornell University** Advised by Nicola Dell and Deborah Estrin.
- 2017 2019 M.S. Information Systems, Health Tech specialization, Cornell Tech GPA: 3.9/4.0 Relevant coursework: Applied Machine Learning, Deep Learning, Natural Language Processing, Human-Computer Interaction, Interactive Device Design.

 Advised by Deborah Estrin and Nicola Dell.
- 2010 2014 B.A. Ecology & Evolutionary Biology, Princeton University GPA: 3.5/4.0 Concentration in Global Health and Health Policy. Studied epidemiology, journalism and social policy with a focus on predictive modeling of infectious disease epidemics. Advised by Bryan Grenfell and Tiffany Bogich.

PUBLICATIONS

- 1. **Tseng, E.,** Okeke, F., Sterling, M., and Dell, N. "We can learn. Why not?" Challenges and Opportunities in Designing for Equity for Home Health Aides. ACM Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI '20). To appear, April 2020.
- 2. Freed, D.*, Havron, S.*, **Tseng, E.,** Gallardo, A., Chatterjee, R., Ristenpart, T., and Dell, N. "Is my phone hacked?" Analyzing Clinical Computer Security Interventions with Survivors of Intimate Partner Violence. Proceedings of the ACM on Human-Computer Interaction: Vol. 1 Issue CSCW. 2019. pdf. Best Paper Honorable Mention.
- 3. Okeke, F., **Tseng, E.,** Piantella, B., Brown, M., Kaur, H., Sterling, M., and Dell, N. *Technology, Home Health Care, and Heart Failure: A Qualitative Analysis with Multiple Stakeholders*. ACM SIGCAS Conference on Computing & Sustainable Societies (COMPASS '19). pdf.

ACADEMIC AWARDS

- 2019 Cornell University Information Science Department Fellowship
 One-year doctoral fellowship awarded in recognition of exceptional preparation and
 promise (top 1.5% of applicants).
- 2017 Cornell Tech Merit Scholarship Two-year merit award for Master's-level study.
- 2014 Princeton University Department of Ecology & Evolutionary Biology Senior Thesis Award -- Mathematical Modeling

CURRENT RESEARCH

Understanding online abuser communities in intimate partner violence (IPV) 7/2019 - present PIs: Nicola Dell, Ph.D. and Thomas Ristenpart, Ph.D. (Cornell Tech)

 Building a longitudinal web scraping pipeline for collecting "in-the-wild" data from online forums, bulletin boards, and other social technologies where abusers share tips on how to enact technology-mediated IPV.

Clinical computer security for victims and survivors of IPV

8/2018 - present

PIs: Nicola Dell, Ph.D. and Thomas Ristenpart, Ph.D. (Cornell Tech)

- Conducting a field study of a "tech clinic" intervention for victims of IPV in New York City, in partnership with the Mayor's Office to End Domestic and Gender-Based Violence.
- Co-authored paper contextualizing resultant learnings in the broader literature on technology for social justice and computer-supported consultative work [1].

Community-engaged technology design to support home health aides (HHAs) caring for adults with heart failure

8/2018 - present

PI: Nicola Dell, Ph.D. (Cornell Tech)

- Performed qualitative analysis of interviews with 50+ HHAs, nurses, physicians and social workers to understand the technology ecosystem around the home care of patients recovering from heart failure.
- Co-authored paper contextualizing resultant themes in the broader literature on technology in coordinated care environments [2].
- Designed and executed a participatory design study with HHAs, nurses, and other stakeholders.
- Built a functional prototype, from wireframes to application, for a tablet-based tool facilitating communication, data collection and decision support for HCWs in the field.

Designing online psychotherapy platforms

7/2018 - present

PI: George Nitzburg, Ph.D. (Teachers' College, Columbia University)

- Conducted a mixed-methods analysis of 19,000 messages sent between patients and providers on a widely used and commercially available platform for online psychotherapy.
- Co-authored paper contextualizing resultant themes in the broader literature on computer-mediated communication and synthesizing design recommendations for mental health technologies [in submission for an ACM conference]

PAST RESEARCH

Extracting family history from unstructured clinical notes

8/2018

- Developed a combined rule-based and statistical model (LSTM-CRF) extracting family history information from unstructured text in patient information questionnaires.
- Awarded student travel grant to present at the OHNLP/BioCreativ workshop at ACM-BCB 2018.

Evaluating the usability of a personal data filtering interface

3/2018 - 6/2018

PI: Deborah Estrin, Ph.D. (Cornell Tech)

- Conducted a controlled experiment via Amazon Mechanical Turk HITs evaluating the usability of an interface for filtering sensitive data from a user's Google Takeout export, with the goal of providing sanitized personal data to researchers. [in submission]
- Performed semi-structured interviews to reveal usability and privacy issues around the tool.

Prototyping a tool for real-time smartphone-based mood tracking

1/2018 - 6/2018

PI: JP Pollak, Ph.D. (Cornell Tech)

- Performed a literature review assessing prior computational approaches to treating anxiety.
- Prototyped and tested an intentive computing tool building on the hardware interface of an iPhone for logging emotional states in real time.
- Performed observational studies and semi-structured interviews to investigate the usability and utility of the tool for managing subthreshold and generalized anxiety.

Modeling the dynamics of enterovirus-71 in Taiwan: An application of the TSIR model

2014

PI: Bryan Grenfell, Ph.D. (Princeton University)

- Developed a time-series model predicting the impact of vaccination on enterovirus infection rates in Taiwan based on data from the Taiwanese CDC. [poster]
- Awarded departmental prize for excellence in mathematical modeling.

RELEVANT WORK EXPERIENCE

Freelance Software Designer & Developer, New York, NY

2017 - present

- Designed and developed a recipe management tool for the Thomas Keller Restaurant Group.
- Developed a Chrome extension providing online news readers with articles from contrasting political viewpoints for civic media startup Bridge the Media.

Pfizer, Inc., New York, NY

Summer Associate

6/2018 - 8/2018

- Led a team of UX researchers and technologists to synthesize user stories, product requirements and storyboards for a care navigation product addressing health disparities within the Welsh NHS.
- Interviewed domain experts on the feasibility of a consumer voice product for patient support.

Biomeme, Inc., Philadelphia, PA

Product & Business Development Associate

8/2014 - 6/2016

- Developed an at-home sexual health diagnostic for a national reproductive healthcare provider.
- Developed a point-of-care influenza diagnostic with a federal disease control agency, resulting in a pilot program in a clinic network in Nairobi, Kenya.
- Conducted UX studies to guide development of a consumer-facing tool for personal DNA analysis.

Oxford University Clinical Research Unit (OUCRU), Ho Chi Minh City, Vietnam

Research Intern

5/2013 - 8/2013

- Conducted literature reviews, performed data analyses (R) and mapped patient enrollment (GIS, Illustrator) for ongoing clinical studies at a tertiary tuberculosis hospital.
- Funded by the Health Grand Challenge at the Center for Health & Wellbeing at Princeton University.

Doctors Without Borders / Medecins Sans Frontieres (MSF), New York, NY

Editorial & Multimedia Intern

5/2011 - 8/2011, 5/2012 - 8/2012

- Produced audio, video and web features as part of the Editorial team at MSF-USA.
- Conducted interviews with MSF field staff, including doctors, nurses, logisticians and administrators.

The Daily Princetonian, Princeton, NJ

Managing Editor

01/2013 - 01/2014

- Led 100+ staff of a collegiate news organization publishing in print 5x/week and online 24/7.
- Built web and data journalism departments, and expanded the paper's multimedia capabilities.

TEACHING EXPERIENCE

Cornell Tech at Cornell University, New York, NY

Teaching Assistant, INFO 6410 / CS 5682: HCI & Design, Professor Nicola DellFall 2019Grader, CS 5740: Natural Language Processing, Professor Yoav ArtziSpring 2019Lead Teaching Assistant, Product Studio, Professor Deborah EstrinFall 2018

Fullstack Academy, New York, NY

Software Engineering Teaching Fellow

5/2017 - 8/2017

- Taught and mentored 80+ students at a selective software engineering bootcamp.
- Delivered a 10-minute talk introducing principles of inclusive design and web accessibility for front-end developers: https://youtu.be/NQP8yg81KZ8

ADDITIONAL LEADERSHIP EXPERIENCE

HealthTech.NYC, 2018-19 Co-Organizer

• Curated a speaker series for engineers, designers, clinicians and academics in the New York City health tech ecosystem.

Venture for America, 2014 Fellow

• Elected to the 2016-17 Alumni Board to support programs providing an onramp to entrepreneurship for historically disadvantaged communities.

SKILLS

- *Human-Centered Design* | Interviewing, contextual enquiry, survey design, thematic analysis, prototyping (Sketch, Photoshop, Illustrator, InDesign, InVision)
- *Software Development* | Full-stack software engineering (JavaScript, Node.JS, React, HTML, CSS/Sass), Agile development
- *Statistical Analysis* | General quantitative analysis and modeling (Python, R, MATLAB), machine learning (scikit-learn, Dynet, Tensorflow)
- Communication | Writing, editing, public speaking, multimedia production (audio and video)
- Research | Literature review, study protocol design, IRB submission, paper-writing